<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for the speedy raising of monies, for compleating and maintaining the army under the immediate command of Robert Earl of Essex, Lord Generall of the forces raised by the Parliament. Assessed in such manner as is within expressed. Ordered by the Commons of Parliament, that this ordinance be forthwith printed and published. Hen. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E39_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21570</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871452</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155073</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155073)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 7:E39[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for the speedy raising of monies, for compleating and maintaining the army under the immediate command of Robert Earl of Essex, Lord Generall of the forces raised by the Parliament. Assessed in such manner as is within expressed. Ordered by the Commons of Parliament, that this ordinance be forthwith printed and published. Hen. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 7-12, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Husbands,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>March 28. 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>With an order to print on final leaf.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Finance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Finance, Public --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155073:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ORDINANCE OF THE Lords and Commons Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, For the ſpeedy raiſing of Monies, for Compleating and maintaining the <hi>Army</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the immediate Command of <hi>ROBERT</hi> Earle of <hi>ESSEX,</hi> Lord Generall of the Forces raiſed by the PARLIAMENT. Aſſeſſed in ſuch manner as is within Expreſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="order">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ordered by the Commons in Parliament, that this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen. Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Edward Husbands.</hi> March 28. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb facs="tcp:155073:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:155073:2"/>
            <head>Die Martis, Martii 26 1644. <hi>An</hi> Ordinance <hi>of the</hi> Lords <hi>and</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons <hi>in Parliament aſſembled, for the ſpeedy compleating and maintaining of the Army under the immediate command of</hi> Robert <hi>Earl of</hi> Eſſex, <hi>Lord Generall of the Forces raiſed by the Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHereas the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, taking into conſideration the neceſſity of ſpeedy recruiting the Army under the immediate command of the Lord Generall, the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> have by an Ordinance of the firſt of this inſtant <hi>February,</hi> 1643. Entituled, <hi>An</hi> Ordinance <hi>for the preſent recruiting of the Army under the immediate command of the Earle of</hi> Eſſex <hi>Lord Generall,</hi> Ordained, that the ſaid Army ſhal be forthwith recruited, unto the number of ſeven thouſand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſoot, beſides Officers, and 3000. horſe, beſides Officers; and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155073:3"/>ſhall conſiſt of ſeven Regiments of foot, and ſix Regiments of horſe, with a ſuitable train of Artillery: and to that end have ordained, that the ſumme of twenty thouſand pounds be forthwith provided out of the Exciſe, or elſewhere, and paid to the Treaſurer of War, for the purpoſes aforeſaid; And do further by the ſaid Ordinance declare, that they intend ſuddenly to ſettle a conſtant pay for the ſaid Army, and that upon the recruiting thereof, care ſhall be taken for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating and reforming thereof. In purſuance of which Ordinance, the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in the Parliament, taking the ſame into their ſerious conſideration, have ordained, and be it ordained by the ſaid Lords and Commons, That the ſaid Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> ſhall diſpoſe of the ſaid 7500. foot-ſouldiers into ſeven Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereof one Regiment, which is to be the Lord Generalls Regiment, ſhall conſiſt of 1500. ſouldiers, and ſhall be divided into twelve Companies; and each of the other ſix Regiments ſhall conſiſt of 1000. ſouldiers a peece: and every of the ſix Regiments ſhall be divided into eight Companies, and no more; and the ſaid 3000. horſe ſhall be diſpoſed into ſix Regiments, every of which Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall conſiſt of 500. Troopers, beſides Officers, and be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into ſix Troopes; whereof the Colonels Troope ſhall conſiſt of one hundred Troopers, beſides Officers, and each of the other five Troopes of fourſcore Troopers a peece, beſides Officers: And it is further ordained by the ſaid Lords and Commons, that the ſumme of 30504 l' ſhall be raiſed and paid in manner and form as is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after mentioned, for the maintenance and payment of the ſaid Army, being recruited, diſpoſed, and regulated as aforeſaid, the trame of Artillery, Reformado Officers, Intelligences and other charges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the ſaid Army: and for proviſion of Armes and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Kingdome for the ſpace of four Moneths, to commence from the twentieth day of <hi>March,</hi> 1643. accompting 28. dayes to the Moneth; that is to ſay, The ſumme of two thouſand pounds ſhall be Monethly paid out of the Monies that come in at <hi>Habberdaſhers Hall,</hi> upon the twentieth part, or otherwiſe, for the time aforeſaid; and that there ſhall be Monethly charged and levied upon the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Hamlets of the <hi>Tower,</hi> the Borough of <hi>Southwarke;</hi> and all other Pariſhes and places within the Lines of Communication and weekely Bills of Mortality, the ſumme of — 6962 <abbr>l'</abbr> — 04 <abbr>s</abbr> — 00</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155073:3"/>
Upon the County of <hi>Midleſex</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſaid limits, the ſumme of 1097 <abbr>l'</abbr> — 11 <abbr>s</abbr> — 00</p>
            <p>And that the ſumme of—20444 <abbr>l'</abbr> — 5 <abbr>s</abbr> — 00 being the Reſidue of the ſaid ſumme of — 30504 <abbr>l'</abbr> ſhall be Monethly paid out of the Exciſe for the time aforeſaid, whereof 18940 <abbr>l'</abbr> — 5 <abbr>s</abbr> — 0 ſhall be for payment of the ſaid Army, and 1504 <abbr>l'</abbr> being the Reſidue of the ſaid ſumme, ſhall be imployed for the proviſion of the Armes and Ammunition for the Kingdome. And this Ordinance ſhall be a ſufficient Warrant, as well to the Committee at <hi>Habberdaſhers Hall,</hi> as to the Commiſſiones of Exciſe, to pay unto Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard,</hi> Bar. Treaſurer at war, the ſaid ſeverall ſummes of money, and to advance the ſame by way of loan, and to pay themſelves again out of the growing profits thereof: And that the ſaid ſeverall ſummes of money may be duly raiſed, levied, and paid, as hereafter is directed, Be it farther ordained by the ſaid Lords and Commons, that the perſons hereafter named, ſhall be Committees for the Cities, Countes, and Places aforeſaid; that is to ſay, For the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and the Liberties thereof, the Lord Major and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men onely, and ſuch as they ſhall nominate: And the Lord Major and Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> and ſix ſuch perſons of every of the Sub-Committees for the <hi>Millitia</hi> within the Lines of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and weekly Bills of Mortality, as the ſaid ſeverall and reſpective Committees ſhall nominate and appoint for this ſervice, and the former Committees named in the Ordinance for the laſt two Moneths Aſſeſſement for the City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Burrough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> Hamlets of the <hi>Tower,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces within the Line of Communication and weekly Bills of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, without the City of <hi>London</hi> and Liberties thereof, ſhall be Committees for the ſaid City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Burrough of <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark,</hi> Hamlets of the <hi>Tower,</hi> and the other places aforeſaid, without the City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Liberties therof: And for the County of <hi>MIDDLESEX,</hi> without the limits aforeſaid;</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Vane,</hi> Knight, ſir <hi>Gilbert Gerrard</hi> Baron. ſir <hi>Edward Barkham,</hi> Knight and Baronet, ſir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155073:4"/>Fowler,</hi> Knight and Baronet, ſir <hi>Richard Sprignall</hi> Baronet, the Lievtenant of the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London</hi> for the time being, ſir <hi>Iohn Danvers,</hi> ſir <hi>Iohn Franklyn,</hi> ſir <hi>Iohn Hepiſley,</hi> ſir <hi>Iames Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington,</hi> ſir <hi>William Roberts,</hi> Knights, <hi>Laurence Whittacre, Iohn Huxley, Thomas Wilcox, Iohn Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, Richard Downton, Iohn Browne</hi> Clerke of the Parliament, <hi>Iuſtiman Paget,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Swallow</hi> Eſquires, ſhall be Committees, which ſaid ſeverall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Committees of the ſeverall and reſpective Cities, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and places aforeſaid, ſhall within two dayes next enſuing the publication hereof, meet together at ſome convenient place, in every of the ſaid Cities, Countie and places, and afterwards ſeven of them at the leaſt, ſhall twice in every weeke at the leaſt, meet at ſuch convenient places as they ſhall thinke fit, for the more ſpeedy execution of this Ordinance: and the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Committees are hereby required and authorized at the dayes and places of their firſt meetings, to divide and apportion the ſeverall ſummes of money, appointed by this Ordinance to be levied for the maintenance of the ſaid Army upon the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and reſpective Wards, Diviſions, Hundreds, Lathes, and Wapentakes within the ſeverall Cities, Countie, and places aforeſaid, according to the uſuall proportions and diviſions of Rates in the ſaid places; and likewiſe ſhall, and may there agree to divide and ſever themſelves for the better execution of this Ordinance, into ſuch Wards, Hundreds, places and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions within their reſpective Cities, Countie and places, as to them ſhall ſeeme expedient, And to take to their aſſiſtance for the more ſpeedy execution of the ſaid ſervice in their ſeverall diviſions, ſuch able and ſufficient perſons as they ſhall think fit, and to aſſemble and meet as often as to them ſhall ſeem good, and forthwith the ſaid Committees, or any two or more of them reſpectively, are hereby authorized and required, to direct their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155073:4"/>Warrants to ſuch number of perſons as they ſhall thinke fit within their ſeverall and reſpective diviſions, to be Aſſeſſours of the ſaid Rates, which ſaid perſons are hereby authorized and required to aſſeſſe all and every perſon and perſons, having any reall or perſonall eſtate within the limits, circuits and bounds of their reſpective diviſions, according to the Rate and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion in this Ordinance mentioned.</p>
            <p>And be it further <hi>Ordained</hi> by the ſaid Lords and Commons, that the ſeverall ſummes of Money before mentioned, and all other ſummes which ſhall be hereafter aſſeſſed or taken upon the ſeverall Cities, County, and Places aforeſaid, ſhall be aſſeſſed and taken both for Lands and goods, upon ſuch perſons and eſtates, and in ſuch manner and forme as is directed for the weekly Aſſeſſement, in an Ordinance of Parliament, of the fourth day of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt intituled, <hi>An</hi> Ordinance <hi>of both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the ſpeedy rayſing and Leavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of money, for the Maintenance of the Army raiſed by the Parliament, and other great affaires of the Common-wealth by a weekly Aſſeſſment.</hi> And to the end the ſaid rates by equally and indifferently Aſſeſſed, and the monies duly collected, and true Accompt thereof made, The ſaid Aſſeſſors are hereby required within, ſix dayes after ſuch Aſſeſſement made, to deliver two Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of their reſpective Aſſeſſements fairely written and ſubſcribed by them, unto the ſaid reſpective Committees, or to any of them, whereof one to remaine with the ſaid Committee, and the other to be delivered to the Collectors, with Warrants to Levie the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. And the ſaid ſeverall Committees or any two of them are hereby reſpectively Authoriſed from time to time, to nominate one or more ſufficient and honeſt perſons in every diviſion or Alotment, to be Collectors of the ſaid monies ſo Aſſeſſed and rated, which ſaid Collectors are hereby authorized and required to Collect the ſaid monies ſo Aſſeſſed, and the ſaid Committee or any ſix of them are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155073:5"/>hereby Authoriſed to allow and pay unto the ſaid reſpective Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, two pence in the pound for their paines in Collecting the ſaid monies; and one penny in the Pound to their Clerkes for their paines, in faire writing the ſaid Aſſeſſement. And if any perſon ſhall refuſe or neglect to pay any ſumme of money, whereat hee ſhall be rated or Aſſeſſed, that then it ſhall or may be lawfull to and for the ſaid Collectors or any of them, to Leavie the ſumme ſo Aſſeſſed by diſtreſſe and ſale of the goods of ſuch perſons ſo refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or neglecting to pay, deducting the ſumme Aſſeſſed, and the reaſonable charges of diſtrayning, and reſtore the over-plus to the Owner thereof; And to breake open any Houſe, Cheſt, Trunke, Box, or other thing, wherein any ſuch Goods are, and to call to their Aſſiſtance any of the Trained Bands, or any other Forces within the Cities, Countie, and Places, where any reſiſtance ſhall be made, or any other perſon or perſons whatſoever; which ſaid Forces and Perſons are hereby required to be ayding and aſſiſting in the Premiſſes, as they ſhall anſwer the contrary at their perills. And if any queſtion or difference happen upon the taking ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe betweene the Parties diſtrained and diſtraining, the ſame ſhall be ended, and determined by the ſaid Committees or any two of them, and the ſaid ſeverall Committees or any two or more of them, are hereby Authorized and required to uſe ſuch other wayes or meanes for the ſpeedy Leavying of the ſaid Aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as to them ſhall be thought fit. And if any perſon or perſons ſhall purpoſely convey his or their goods or other perſonall Eſtate, whereby the ſumme of Money ſo Aſſeſſed, cannot be Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied according to this Ordinance, then the ſaid reſpective Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees or any two of them are hereby Authorized by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or ſuch other perſons as they ſhall appoint, to Impriſon the perſons, and to Sequeſter the Eſtate of every ſuch perſon, for the Advancement of the ſaid ſervice, and the Tennants of all houſes and lands which ſhall be rated by vertue of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, are hereby required and Authoriſed to pay ſuch ſummes of money as ſhall be rated upon every ſuch houſe and Lands, and to deduct out of their rents ſo much of the ſaid rates, as in reſpect of the Rents of every ſuch Houſe and Lands, the Landlords ſhould or ought to pay or beare; and the Landlords both mediate and immediate according to their reſpective Intereſt, are hereby
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155073:5"/>required to allow ſuch deductions and payments upon the Receipt of the Reſidue of their Rents, and to give Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances for the whole Rents, as if no deductions had beene made. And if any Landlord ſhall refuſe to make ſuch Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance or deduction, or to give ſuch acquittances, then the reſpective Committees for the Sequeſtrations in the Cities, County, and places aforeſaid upon proofe thereof made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, are hereby Authorized for every time they ſhall ſo refuſe, to ſeize and ſequeſter for the ſervice aforeſaid one full halfe yeares Rent payable to ſuch perſons ſo refuſing, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the ſame, the ſumme of money ſo paid by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as aforeſaid; And if any difference ſhall ariſe betweene Landlord and Tenant, or any other concerning the ſaid Rates, the ſaid ſeverall Committees, or any two of them in their ſeverall Diviſions, have hereby power to ſettle the ſame as they ſhall thinke fit; And the ſaid Collectours and every of them are hereby required from time to time, to pay ſuch ſumme and ſummes of money as ſhall be by them Collected by vertue of this Ordinance to the ſaid Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard,</hi> Treaſurer at Warres.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained, that the ſeverall and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Committees, in the ſeverall Cities, County and places aforeſaid, ſhall and are hereby required, to cauſe one Moneths Aſſeſſement according to this Ordinance to be aſſeſſed, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied, collected, and paid unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard,</hi> at or before the ſeventeenth day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1644. which ſaid Moneths Aſſeſſement ſhall be reckoned as the firſt Moneths pay for the ſaid Army, due out of the ſaid Cities, County and places aforeſaid by vertue of this Ordinance. And the ſaid ſeverall Committees are hereby required to take ſpeciall care that the ſaid monethly Aſſeſſements be conſtantly leavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, collected, and paid to the ſaid Sir <hi>Gilbert Gerard,</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer at warres, once in every Moneth after the ſaid ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of <hi>April,</hi> during the continuance of the terme mentioned in this Ordinance, accounting 28 dayes and no more to each Moneth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155073:6"/>
And be it further ordained by the Lords and Commons, That foure fit and able perſons ſhall be elected to be imployed as Commiſſioners from both Houſes of Parliament, and the ſaid Cities and County aforeſaid; to be conſtantly abiding in the ſaid Army, which perſons ſhall be elected and nominated by the Houſe of Commons. Which ſaid Commiſſioners ſo appointed to attend the Army ſhall have each of them the ſumme of twenty ſhillings for every day they ſhall attend the ſaid ſervice to be paid by the ſaid Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminſter,</hi> and the County of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and places afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>And to that purpoſe it is further Ordained by the Lords and Commons, that the ſaid ſeverall Committees hereby no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated, or any ſixe of them in the reſpective Cities, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and places aforeſaid ſhall have power, and are hereby Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized to impoſe a rate upon the ſaid ſeverall and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Cities, County, and places aforeſaid, for the payment of the ſaid Allowance of Twenty ſhilling, by the day to the ſaid Commiſſioners to be Aſſeſſed, levied and collected, as the other Aſſeſſement in this Ordinance mentioned is to be Aſſeſſed, levied and collected.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained, That the Commiſſioners ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to reſide in the Army ſhall take ſpeciall care that they keepe conſtant correſpondence with the two Houſes of Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or with ſuch as they ſhall nominate, and with the reſpective Committees of the reſpective Cities, County, and places aforeſaid; And that they take ſuch courſe, that no Commander or Officer ſhall rerceive any pay, but ſuch as duly attend their charge; And it is deſired that the ſaid Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> doe admit to his counſell for the purpoſes aforeſaid, the ſaid Commiſſioners reſiding in his Army to adviſe with them, and arme them with power to view and examine the Muſters of the ſaid Army, and to take ſuch courſe as ſhall be thought moſt fit for the preventing of dead Payments, falſe Muſters, free quartering without Warrants, Plundring, ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Horſes, ſelling, ſpoyling, or imbezelling of Horſes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155073:6"/>or Armes, and for the avoyding of any other miſdemeanour which may turne to the prejudice of the Common-wealth; And that the ſaid Commiſſioners ſhall once in fifteene dayes certifie the ſtate of the Army, and give an accompt of their proceedings unto the Parliament, or to ſuch Committees as they ſhall appoint for that purpoſe; And ſhall likewiſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie what further Inſtructions ſhall be agreed upon by the Counſell of VVarre touching the ſame; And whereas ſince the beginning of this warre, great and unneceſſary waſte hath beene made of Horſes and Armes, by the negligence and abuſe of Souldiers, whereby the Kingdome will become una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to continue Tillage, and to recruite the Armies, unleſſe ſome ſpeedy proviſion be made to prevent the ſame.</p>
            <p>Be it forther ordained. That the Captaines both of Horſe and Foote out of the pay due to themſelves and their Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are to make good all the Horſes, and Horſe-armes, and Foot-armes, that ſhall be loſt and imbezilled by them, or any under their command, unleſſe they can make it appeare that they were loſt in ſervice againſt the enemy. Provided, That no Officer ſhall be obliged to make good the Armes or Horſe of any Souldiers that ſhall runne away from their Colours, if the ſaid Officers ſhall within twenty foure houres after the departure of ſuch Souldier, give notice thereof to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners reſiding in the Army, to the end ſpeedy courſe may be taken for their apprehending and puniſhment.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained by the ſaid Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, That if any perſon or perſons ſhall wilfully neglect, or refuſe to performe his duty in the due and ſpeedy Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this preſent Ordinance, the ſaid reſpective Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, or any five of them, have hereby Power to impoſe upon ſuch perſon or perſons ſo refuſing or neglecting their duties, ſuch Fine or Fines as to them ſhall be thought fit, and cauſe the ſame to be levied by diſtreſſe and ſale of goods in manner and forme aforeſaid; Provided, That no Fine to be impoſed upon any of the ſaid Committees, ſhall not for any one Offence exceed the ſumme of forty ſhillings; And that no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155073:7"/>fine to be impoſed upon any Aſſeſſor, Collector or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be immployed by the ſaid Committees in the ſaid ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, ſhall for any offence exceede the ſumme of forty ſhillings. And that no priviledged place or perſon within the Citties, County and places aforeſaid, ſhalbe exempted from the ſaid Aſſeſſements and Taxes.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained that the ſaid ſeverall and reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Committees and every of them ſhall from time to time give a true and perfect Accompt of all their doings and proceedings in the execution of this Ordinance to the two Houſes of Parliament, or to ſuch perſons as they ſhall appoint.</p>
            <p>And it is further Ordained that if any perſon or perſons, ſhal buy or take to pawne or receive any of the Armes, or horſe, belonging to any Common ſouldier or Officer under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of a Coronett or Enſigne, that ſuch perſon or perſons ſhall forfeite ſuch Armes, and horſe, and treble the value of ſuch Armes and horſe, and ſhalbe impriſoned by the ſpace of twenty eight dayes without Baile or maineprize. And the Lord Generall is hereby enabled by himſelfe or ſuch as hee ſhall appoint, if it be within the quarters of his Army, and the deputy Lievtenants, and Juſtices of the peace, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees of Parliament or any one of them in their reſpective Lymits ſhall have power, and are hereby authoriſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the fact and upon proofe thereof to ſee this clauſe duly executed.</p>
            <p>And it is further Ordained by the ſaid Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that every Captaine both of horſe and foot, and every other inferior and ſuperior Officer, or other in the ſaid Army, whoſe pay comes to ten ſhillings a day or above ſhall take but halfe the pay due to him, and ſhall reſpit the other halfe upon the publique faith untill theſe unnaturall warres be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and every Officer or other that is to have five ſhillings a day or above, and under ten ſhillings, ſhall accept of two thirds of the pay due to him, and ſhall reſpitt one third part upon the pulike faith untill theſe unnaturall Warres ſhalbe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:155073:7"/>ended, And when there is three moneths pay due to any of them, or more, a certificate thereof from the ſaid Earle, ſhalbe ſufficient to demand the ſaid Moneyes oweing upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique faith as aforeſaid, and it is ordained that the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall be deſired, and the ſaid Commiſſioners are hereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and injoyned, to ſee the Articles touching the muſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and payment of the Army, and concerning horſe, Arms, and ammunition, and all ſuch further directions as from time to time concerning the Army, and the affairesthereof, ſhalbe recommended to their care by one or either Houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, be duly obſerved, and to take care that the Country be not charged with free quarter, and whereas the army now under the imediate command of the Lord Generall doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of many more Regiments both of horſe and foote, and conſequently of more Officers then can have imployment as the Army is to be reduced by this Ordinance; By means whereof divers Commanders and Officers, who are very worthy and deſirous of the ſervice, cannot at preſent have imployment according to their qualities, for whoſe ſupport and maintenance ſome competent proviſion is to be made untill there ſhalbe places and imployments for them. It is therefore ordained and declared by the Lords and Commons in Parliament, and the Lord Generall is hereby authorized to entertaine ſuch and ſo many of the ſaid Officers as by the Lord Generall ſhalbe thought fit, and ſhalbe by this occaſion out of imployment, into the condition of reformadoe Officers, and ſhall forme them under Command, into two troopes of horſe not exceeding 100. in each troope beſides Officers, in augumentation of the Lord Generals owne Regiment; which Officers ſo formed, and attending the ſervice, ſhall have ſuch entertainements, and in ſuch manner as is hereafter expreſſed, that is to ſay, the ſaid Officers reſpectively according to the quality of their late imployment, ſhall each of them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively be paid, from time to time as the reſt of the Army is paid one fourth part of his perſonall entertainement, according to the liſt or eſtabliſhment of the Army, over and beſides the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155073:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155073:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:155073:9"/>ordinary pay of troopers, Harquebuſheers, and one other fourth part of his perſonall entertainement according to the ſaid liſt and eſtabliſhment of the Army, ſhalbe reſpited upon the publique faith, untill theſe unnaturall warrs be ended.</p>
            <p>Laſtly be it ordained and declared by the authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that this Army under the immediate Command of the Lord Generall the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> ſhalbe ſubject to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and directions of both Houſes of Parliament, or the Committee of both Kingdomes, according to the Ordinance that doth eſtabliſh that Committee. Provided alwayes that ſuch rates and aſſeſſements, as ſhall be made by virtue of this Ordinance upon any members, Aſſiſtants or Attendants upon either of the Houſes of Parliament, ſhall before the ſame bee leavied, bee preſented to the reſpective Houſes, whoſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Aſſiſtants, or Attendants, ſhall be concerned therein reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, and by ſuch reſpective Houſe allowed and approved of, any thing in this Ordinance to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:155073:9"/>
            <p>Ordered by the Commons in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament that this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance be forthwith printed and publiſhed</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elfynge. <hi>Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
